Guide to the Gaston Lachaise Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gaston Lachaise collection
1867-1979
YCAL MSS 434
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.96
(16 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
Collection contains correspondence, writings, photographs, scrapbooks, and other materials documenting the life and artistic career of French sculptor Gaston Lachaise. General Correspondence consists chiefly of incoming and outgoing correspondence between Gaston Lachaise and others, including family, friends, artists and writers, art critics and patrons, and cultural institutions. The correspondence features 567 outgoing letters from Lachaise to his wife Isabel Dutaud Nagle Lachaise, dating from 1910 to 1934, and incoming correspondence from New York area artists and cultural figures of the 1920s and 1930s. There are a few pieces of writing by Lachaise and several works by others. Photographs include over 200 black-and-white images of Lachaise, family members, and friends, and of artwork by Lachaise and Pierre-Robert Christophe. Scrapbooks and printed ephemera document publicity and critical reception of Lachaise's work from the 1920s through 1970s and other materials, such as lists of Lachaise's work and the names of private owners, identify his work and document its custodial history. Third-party correspondence can be found between Gaston Lachaise's sister Allys and Lincoln Kirstein and others.
Lachaise, Gaston, 1882-1935
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Isabel Lachaise (1949 and 1951), Lincoln Kirstein (1949), and the estate of Allys Lachaise (1968), with additional small gifts and purchases from other sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Miscrofilm available for portions of the collection.
Associated Materials
The Lachaise Foundation, 10 Federal Street, Boston, Massachusetts, 02110.
Gaston Lachaise (1882-1935)
Gaston Lachaise was a French sculptor best known for his female nudes. Born in Paris, Lachaise trained in the decorative arts, and from 1898 to 1904, studied sculpture at the École des Beaux-Arts. He began his artistic career as a designer of Art Nouveau decorative objects for the French jeweler René Lalique. After falling in love with an American woman, Isabel Dutaud Nagle, Lachaise immigrated to the United States in 1906, working first in Boston for H. H. Kitson, an academic sculptor of military monuments, before moving to New York City in 1912.
Biographical information on Gaston Lachaise taken from the Wikipedia entry on Lachaise (accessed 22 December 2010) and the biography of Lachaise by The Lachaise Foundation (accessed 22 December 2010).
Scope and Contents
The Gaston Lachaise collection contains correspondence, writings, photographs, scrapbooks, and other materials documenting the life and artistic career of French sculptor Gaston Lachaise. The General Correspondence in the collection consists chiefly of incoming and outgoing correspondence between Gaston Lachaise and others, including family, friends, artists and writers, art critics and patrons, and cultural institutions. The correspondence features 567 outgoing letters from Lachaise to his wife Isabel Dutaud Nagle Lachaise,dating from 1910 to 1934, and incoming correspondence from New York area artists and cultural figures of the 1920s and 1930s. There are only a few pieces of writing by Lachaise, including a typescript draft of the essay "A Comment on My Sculpture" published in Creative Art in 1928, and several works by others relating to Lachaise. Photographs include over 200 black-and-white images of Lachaise, family members, and friends, and of artwork by Lachaise and French sculptor Pierre-Robert Christophe. Scrapbooks and printed ephemera document publicity and critical reception of Lachaise's work from the 1920s through 1970s and other materials, such as lists of Lachaise's work and the names of private owners, identify his work and document its custodial history. Lastly, third-party correspondence can be found between Gaston Lachaise's sister Allys and Lincoln Kirstein and others.
Arrangement
Organized into seven series: I. General Correspondence, 1906-1957. II. Writings, 1927-1964. III. Photographs, 1867-1944. IV. Scrapbooks, 1918-1945. V. Personal Papers, 1882-1979. VI. Allys Lachaise Correspondence, 1905-1967. VII. Lincoln Kirstein Correspondence Relating to Gaston and Isabel Lachaise, 1933-1961.
Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Sculptors; Sculpture, French -- 20th Century; Sculpture, Modern -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Artists; Christophe, Pierre-Robert; Kirstein, Lincoln, 1907-1996; Lachaise, Allys; Lachaise, Gaston, 1882-1935; Lachaise, Isabel Dutaud Nagle
- General Correspondence, 1906-1957; Series I; 2.71; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence consists chiefly of incoming and outgoing correspondence between Gaston Lachaise and others, including family, friends, artists and writers, art critics and patrons, and cultural institutions. The series features 567 original outgoing letters from Lachaise to his wife Isabel Dutaud Nagle Lachaise, dating from 1910 to 1934, and incoming correspondence from New York area artists and cultural figures of the 1920s and 1930s, including Albert Eugene Gallatin, Marsden Hartley, Lincoln Kirstein, Gorham Munson, Dorothy Norman, Alfred Stieglitz, Carrie Stettheimer, Carl Van Vechten, Edward Warburg, and Marguerite Zorach.
  There are a number of letters addressed to Lachaise's wife, most of which follow his death in 1935.
  - "A" general, 1923-1938 (Box 1)
    Includes letters from H. B. Alexander, Winslow Amers, and Merle Armitage
  - Adlow, Dorothy, undated (Box 1)
  - Allen, Atkinson and Charlotte Whitney, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1928, 1940 (Box 1)
  - "B" general, 1928, undated (Box 1)
    Includes letter from Lucile Blanch
  - Bacon, Peggy, 1923 February 29 (Box 1)
  - Barr, Alfred Hamilton, 1930 November 21 (Box 1)
  - Beebe, William, 1929 February 8 (Box 1)
  - Bosworth, Welles, 1923-1929 (Box 1)
  - Bourgeois Galleries, 1917-1922 (Box 1)
  - Brancusi, Constantin, undated (Box 1)
  - Brown, Slater, undated (Box 1)
  - Buhlig, Richard, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Burke, Kenneth, 1932 October 27 (Box 1)
  - "C" general, 1919-1922, undated (Box 1)
    Includes letters from G. Alan Chidsey, Mary Churchill, L. Pierce Clark, Jacques Copeau, and Henry Cowell
  - Christophe, Pierre-Robert, 1907-1909 (Box 1)
  - Claflin, Agnes Rindge, 1937, undated (Box 1)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1924 June 27 (Box 1)
  - Crane, Hart and Grace Hart, 1924-1933 (Box 1)
  - Craven, Thomas, 1928 March 25 (Box 1)
  - Creative Art, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Crowninshield, Frank, 1938 (Box 1)
  - "D" general, 1935, undated (Box 1)
  - Dove, Arthur, 1928, undated (Box 1)
  - Dreier, Katherine Sophie, 1926 October 23 (Box 1)
  - "E" general, 1929, 1936 (Box 1)
    Includes letter from Arthur Egner
  - Fiene, Ernest and Jeanette, 1926, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Force, Juliana, 1935-1945 (Box 1)
  - French, Daniel Chester, 1918 June 28 (Box 1)
  - Frost, Rosamund, 1937 May 24 (Box 1)
  - "G" general, 1930, undated (Box 1)
    Includes letter from Eva Gauthier
  - Gallatin, A. E. (Albert Eugene), 1924-1927, undated (Box 1)
  - Goodwin, Philip Lippincott, 1927-1935 (Box 1)
  - Goodyear, A. Conger (Anson Conger), 1934 June 21 (Box 1)
  - Gould, Joe, 1930 (Box 1)
  - "H" general, 1931-1941, undated (Box 1)
    Contains letters from Irwin Heilner, Clarence B. Hill, and Honolulu Academy of Arts
  - Hartley, Marsden, 1928-1942, undated (Box 1)
    Includes letter from Rosalind Irvine
  - Hartman, C. Bertram, 1935, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Howe, George, 1928, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Iselin, O'Donnell, 1927, undated (Box 1)
  - Ittelson, Miriam, 1932 February 29 (Box 1)
  - James, Rebecca Salsbury, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Jones, Marjorie, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Kahn, Ely Jacques, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1929-1944, undated; 4 (Box 1)
  - Kitson, Henry, 1911 September 9 (Box 1)
  - Knollenberg, Bernhard and Mary Lightfoot Tarleton, 1936, 1957 (Box 1)
  - "L" general, 1922-1937, undated (Box 1)
    Includes letters from Charles Dowing Lay, Julian E. Levi, and Life
  - Lachaise, Allys (sister) and Marie Barré (mother), 1906-1916; 3 (Box 2)
  - Lachaise, Isabel Dutaud Nagle (wife), 1910-1920; 8 (Box 2)
  - Lachaise, Isabel Dutaud Nagle (wife), 1921-1933; 8 (Box 3)
  - Lachaise, Isabel Dutaud Nagle (wife), 1933-1934; 7 (Box 4)
  - Lachaise, Isabel Dutaud Nagle (wife), 1934, undated; 7 (Box 5)
  - Lachaise, Marie Barré (mother), 1908-1934 (Box 5)
  - "M" general, 1928-1938 (Box 5)
    General note
    Includes letters from Robert McCordock and Macmillan Company
  - McBride, Henry, 1928-1935 (Box 5)
  - Marin, John, 1926-1945 (Box 5)
  - Marshall, Lorna J., undated (Box 5)
  - Mayor, A. Hyatt (Alpheus Hyatt), undated (Box 5)
  - Meigs, Arthur I., 1925-1931 (Box 5)
  - Mellquist, Jerome, 1943 September 4 (Box 6)
  - Moncel, Alphonse Emmanuel, 1899 (Box 6)
  - Morgan, Christiana D., undated (Box 6)
  - Morris, George L. K., 1934-1935, undated (Box 6)
  - Munson, Gorham Bert, 1934 January 25 (Box 6)
  - Murray, Henry A., 1935, undated (Box 6)
  - "N" general, 1935, undated (Box 6)
    Includes letter from Reuben Nakian
  - Nagle, Edward (stepson), 1918-1934; 7 (Box 6)
  - Nagle, Edward (stepson), 1933-1935; 2 (Box 7)
  - Norman, Dorothy, 1937-1938 (Box 7)
  - "O" general, 1917, undated (Box 7)
  - "P" general, 1935-1945, undated (Box 7)
  - Paine, Anna Hooker, 1935 (Box 7)
  - Parkes, Kineton, 1922 (Box 7)
  - Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1933 (Box 7)
  - Pierce, Ruth, undated (Box 7)
  - Purdy, W. Frank and Mabel Dulon, 1935-1944 (Box 7)
  - "R" general, 1921-1936, undated (Box 7)
    Includes letters from Rebecca H. Reyher and viscountess Mary Lilian Share Harmsworth Rothermere
  - Rosenfeld, Paul, 1926, 1943 (Box 7)
  - "S" general, 1926-1937, undated (Box 7)
    Includes letters from Paul J. Sachs, Herbert Seligmann, and Carl Sprinchorn
  - Scott, Stevenson, 1928, undated (Box 7)
  - Seldes, Gilbert, 1928-1930, undated (Box 7)
  - Stettheimer, Carrie Walter, 1931 April 11 (Box 7)
  - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1935 October 20 (Box 7)
  - Strand, Paul, 1929-1939 (Box 7)
    Includes third-party letter from Strand to Buffalo Fine Art Museum
  - Thacher, John, 1937 (Box 7)
  - Thayer, Ellen, 1935, undated (Box 7)
  - Thayer, Scofield, 1919-1935 (Box 7)
  - Town Hall (New York, N.Y.), 1937-1939 (Box 7)
  - University of Rochester. Memorial Art Gallery, 1926-1935 (Box 7)
  - Untermeyer, Jean Starr, 1936, undated (Box 7)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1932-1935 (Box 7)
  - "W" general, 1933-1935 (Box 7)
    Includes letters from George Henry Warren Jr., E. Weyhe, and F. A. Whiting Jr.
  - Walker, Hudson, 1937 September 2 (Box 7)
  - Warburg, Edward M. M., 1933-1939 (Box 7)
  - Watson, James S. (James Sibley) and Hildegarde Lasell, 1930-1935, undated (Box 7)
  - Weber, Max, 1941 March 9 (Box 7)
  - Werner, M. R. (Morris Robert), 1933, 1935 (Box 7)
  - Wertheim, Maurice and Alma, 1928, undated (Box 7)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Force, Juliana, Box 1
  - Zorach, Marguerite, 1935 (Box 7)
  - Unidentified, 1909-1935; 2 (Box 7)
- Writings, 1927-1964; Series II; 17
  Organized into three subseries: Writings by Gaston Lachaise, Writings by Allys Lachaise, and Writings by Others.
  Series II. Writings contains a few pieces of writing by Lachaise, including a typescript draft of the essay "A Comment on My Sculpture" published in Creative Art in 1928, and several works by others relating to Lachaise.
  - Writings by Gaston Lachaise
    - [Autobiography], [1931]; 2 (Box 8)
    - "A Comment on My Sculpture", [1928] (Box 8)
    - [On Paul Strand], undated (Box 8)
  - Writings by Allys Lachaise
    - "Collection à Beaune", 1962 (Box 8)
    - "Gaston Lachaise", undated (Box 8)
    - "Gaston: son amour pour les animaux", undated (Box 8)
    - "In and Out of the Dark", 1964 October (Box 8)
  - Writings by Others (Box 8)
    - Gerstein, Evelyn, undated (Box 8)
    - Goodall, Donald B., 1961 August 28 (Box 8)
    - Grant-Stuart, Evelyn, undated (Box 8)
    - Lachaise, Isabel (Dutaud), undated; 4 (Box 8)
    - Nagle, Edward, undated (Box 8)
    - Woodside, B. H., [1927] (Box 8)
- Photographs, 1867-1944; Series III; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arranged into thirteen subdivisions: Photographs of the family of Gaston Lachaise; Photographs of Pierre Christophe, his family, and his work; Photographs of Mr. and Mrs. Jules Billet-Petitjean; Photographs of the d'Orgeval family; Photographs of Marie Lachaise; Photographs of Jean Lachaise; Photographs of Allys Lachaise; Photographs of Gaston Lachaise; Photographs of Gaston Lachaise by Carl Van Vechten; Photographs of early work by Gaston Lachaise in the Collection of Mme. Jeane d'Orgeval; Photographs of sculpture by Gaston Lachaise; and Miscellaneous photographs.
  Series III. Photographs contains over 200 black-and-white photographs, including cabinet cards, with images of Gaston Lachaise, family members, and friends, and of his artwork and the artwork of fellow French sculptor Pierre-Robert Christophe. Photographs are identified on the "List of photographs in the Gaston Lachaise Collection" and arranged numerically.
  The series includes photographs by Carl Van Vechten.
  - "List of photographs in the Gaston Lachaise Collection", undated (Box 8)
  - Photographs, 1867-1944, undated; 15 (Box 8)
  - Photographs, 1867-1944, undated; 49 (Box 9)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 12 Broadside)
- Scrapbooks, 1918-1945; Series IV; 4.59; (5 boxes)
  Arranged chonologically by dates of content.
  Series IV. Scrapbooks contains exhibition catalogues, letters, clippings, and other ephemera relating to the work of Gaston Lachaise. Scrapbook volumes IV and V contain clippings dating from 1935 onward, following Lachaise's death, and were, possibly along with earlier volumes, compiled by Isabel Dutaud Nagle Lachaise.
  - Volume 1, 1918-1926 (Box 13 Oversize)
  - Volume 2, 1927-1929 (Box 14 Oversize)
  - Volume 3, 1930-1934 (Box 15 Oversize)
  - Volume 4, 1935-1940 (Box 16 Oversize)
  - Volume 5, 1941-1945 (Box 17 Oversize)
- Personal Papers, 1882-1980; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series V. Personal Papers contains original artwork, lists identifying artwork by Lachaise, the names of private owners of artwork by Lachaise, a small number of personal documents, and printed ephemera documenting publicity for and critical reception of Lachaise's work from the 1920s through 1970s.
  - Addresses of owners of Gaston Lachaise's work, undated; 2 (Box 10)
  - Bibliography, undated (Box 10)
  - Crayon portrait of Gaston Lachaise by unidentified artist, [circa 1888] (Box 10)
  - Drawing by Gaston Lachaise, 1905 May (Box 10)
  - Gaston Lachaise collection inventories, undated (Box 10)
  - Journal "Reference to Sculpture and Drawings", undated (Box 10)
  - List of exhibition items "At Kraushaar Galleries", undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous personal documents, 1882-1962, undated (Box 10)
  - Printed ephemera, 1921-1980, undated; 6 (Box 10)
- Allys Lachaise Correspondence, 1905-1967; Series VI; 15
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  Series VI. Allys Lachaise Correspondence contains correspondence between Gaston Lachaise's sister Allys and others, as well as additional third-party correspondence between family members and others.
  - Chapman, Alice, 1950 September 4 (Box 11)
  - Caruchet, Isabel, [1911] December 28 (Box 11)
  - Christophe, Pierre-Robert, 1935-1967; 3 (Box 11)
  - Lachaise, Allys to Marie (Barré) Lachaise, 1910-1919 (Box 11)
  - Lachaise, Allys (postcards to her from unidentified correspondents), 1919 (Box 11)
  - Lachaise, Isabel (Dutaud) to Allys Lachaise, 1935-1947 (Box 11)
  - Lachaise, Marie (Barré) to Allys Lachaise, 1911-1916 (Box 11)
  - Lachaise, Marie (Barré) (postcards to her from unidentified correspondents), [1908?]-1919 (Box 11)
  - Lachaise, Isabel (Dutaud) to Marie (Barré) Lachaise, 1909-1935 (Box 11)
  - Moncel, Alphonse Emmanuel to Allys Lachaise, 1905 October 4 (Box 11)
  - Petrov, Basil to Henriette Caruchet, 1948 (Box 11)
  - Petrov, Basil to Pierre-Robert Christophe, 1948 (Box 11)
  - Petrov, Basil to Allys Lachaise, 1947 April 1 (Box 11)
- Lincoln Kirstein Correspondence Relating to Gaston and Isabel Lachaise, 1933-1961; Series VII; 21
  Series VII. Lincoln Kirstein Correspondence contains correspondence between Lincoln Kirstein and others, including carbons of outgoing letters. Most letters date from the mid 1930s, following Lachaise's death in late 1935, and relate to Kirstein's efforts on behalf of Mrs. Isabel Lachaise and the Lachaise estate.
  - Archer, Edmund Minor, 1936 December (Box 11)
  - Barr, Alfred Hamilton, 1936 (Box 11)
  - Buchholz Gallery, 1947 January 24 (Box 11)
  - Draper, Muriel, 1950-1951, undated (Box 11)
  - E. Gargani & Sons, Inc., 1938 (Box 11)
  - ETTL Studios, 1935-1936 (Box 11)
  - Fish, Morris, 1938 February 25 (Box 11)
  - Garfield, Gustave B., 1935, 1938 (Box 11)
  - Goodall, Donald B., 1959-1961 (Box 11)
  - Ingersoll, R. Sturgis (Robert Sturgis), 1935, 1947 (Box 11)
  - Ittleson, Blanche, 1933 November 21 (Box 11)
  - Lincoln Warehouse Corp., 1940-1942 (Box 11)
  - Lukens, Savage & Washburn, 1935 October (Box 11)
  - McIlhenny, Henry P., 1936 (Box 11)
  - Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1933, undated (Box 11)
  - Phillips, John Goodsmith, 1936-1937 (Box 11)
  - Sailors' Snug Harbor (Institution), 1938-1939 (Box 11)
  - Straus, Flora Stieglitz, 1947 March 4 (Box 11)
  - Youtz, Philip Newell, 1937 December (Box 11)
  - Unsorted, 1934-1947, undated; 2 (Box 11)